当我七八十年代在英国长大的时候，尤其是整个八十年代
When I was growing up in England in the 1970s and throughout the 80s in particular
社会各界都特别害怕超级大国之间爆发核战争
there was an almost palpable fear that a nuclear exchange could break out between the superpowers at almost any time
这让包括我在内的很多人都在想，有没有办法能阻止导弹攻击
It caused me and many others around at the time to wonder if there was a way to stop a missile attack
但讲道理这真挺难的
but to be honest it was very literally you could do
你要是住在大城市，或者一个军事基地旁边，这时候来了个洲际导弹
If you lived in a big city or near a military base there was nothing to stop an ICBM or intercontinental
那你基本就凉凉了，英国的话有四分钟预警
ballistic missile once it was on its way and with the four-minute warning we had
你还不如临死前上B站二倍速看一遍这个视频然后给UP主投币点赞关注什么的
here in the UK you might as well just have one last game of Missile Command and hope for a quick end
转眼间过了三十多年，我们现在的世界
Roll around 35 plus years and although we now live in a
核威胁已经没当年那么吓人了
time where the threat from nuclear attack is much less it's still present
即使毛子老实了以后鑫胖那边又挑刺
even if it may have moved to a different area of the globe
那么今天科技进步这么多，咱还有可能拦截导弹吗？
So with the advancement of technology can we stop a missile attack them now once it's started
自从德国在二战后期发明了洲际导弹
Ever since the first missiles were developed by the Germans in the latter part of the Second World War
很多人就特害怕导弹，尤其被导弹炸过的地方
they have struck fear into the heart and many certainly those in the vicinity of a receiving end
主要原因是洲际导弹载荷的运输方式，和飞机或者普通的巡航导弹不一样
The primary reason for this is the way they deliver their payload, unlike planes or cruise missiles
后两者飞的慢，一般都是亚音速，使得它们
which by comparison are quite slow and travel normally at subsonic speed leaving them susceptible to anti-aircraft fire
很容易用地对空导弹或者防空网拦截，但洲际导弹就不一样了
or surface-to-air missiles. An ICBM is usually launched - but the atmosphere
它们直接发射进太空，然后弹头分离，再落回地球
into space where the warhead bit separates from a main body and it falls back to earth
因为这些弹头的速度
Because of the ballistic trajectory the speed of these warheads
即使在进入大气以后仍然高达每小时三万多公里
even when they come through the denser atmosphere is still in a region of 15-20,000 mph,  31,000 km/h
每秒8.6公里，马赫数25左右！
up to five miles or 8.6 kilometers per second around mach 25!
正是这个速度才让它极难拦截，因为一切都是电光火石之间
It's this speed which makes them so difficult to stop because everything happens so fast
侦测这种攻击的发生、落点预测
The detection of an attack, the coordination of countermeasures and the
以及采取拦截措施，都要分秒必争
launch of any defensive options has to happen within minutes and is one of the
使其成为科技、工程领域的天顶科技
most difficult technical and engineering challenges around and that's without the
别忘了攻击方还会配有反拦截措施，这个稍后会说
attackers countermeasures which we'll come to later
想要拦截导弹，就要找出其弱点，为此我们需要
In order to look at stopping a missile we have to find its vulnerabilities and for that we have to
先知道洲际导弹的弹道分为三个阶段
understand its trajectory phrase which is made up of three parts
第一阶段是推进加速段，导弹发射、加速进太空
The first part is the boost phase this is when it's launching and accelerating up to space
导弹大约需要四分钟飞到
that lasts around four minutes taking the missile to a height of around 90 to
150-200公里的高空，接下来是第二阶段——中途阶段（亚轨道飞行阶段）
125 miles around 150 to 200 kilometers. Then there is the second mid-course
在这个阶段里，之前推进的发动机其实已经烧完燃料了，凭惯性飞跃太空
phase this is where the Boost engines burn out and it travels through space
飞过远地点后下落，这也是三个阶段里时间最长的
through the highest point of its trajectory this is also the longest
总共大约20分钟，最后阶段叫再入大气层阶段
phase taking around 20 minutes the third and final phase is the terminal phase
其间弹头再入大气，飞向目标
this is where the warhead re-enters the atmosphere force towards its target this
这个阶段也最短，大概在30秒到一分钟
is also the shortest and lasts around 30 seconds to one a minute.
拦截最先要做的是侦测发射活动
Before anything can be done you have to detect when a launch has happened
今天我们天上有红外的卫星，能时刻监测
Today we have satellites with infrared sensors these are constantly on the lookout for
火箭发射尾焰的热流
the tell-tale heat plume from the rocket engines
在侦查卫星发明之前，唯一的办法就是
Before the advent of the detection satellites the only way to know along to the curd or some early
预警雷达监测快速上升到某一高度的物体
warning radar posts detecting that an object had risen quickly above a certain altitude
这个阶段的导弹是最脆弱的
It's this first boost frames when the missiles are at their most
但也是最难拦截的阶段
vulnerable and ironically their most difficult to get at
虽然开始的时候飞得慢，但加速度大
The rode way are quite slow moving to start with they accelerate extremely rapidly
想拦截导弹，你需要一个更快的导弹
To shoot down the missile you need another even faster missile
问题是发射井都是藏起来的
The problem here is that they could be deep within enemy territory on one of our launchers or
有的还在船上、潜艇上，或者在拦截弹射程外
even at sea long some ships or submarines or too far away from abms
另一种方式是飞机上装高能激光武器
Other types of weapons such as high-power airborne lasers can
但这需要飞机离导弹近一点
down missiles but they have to be relatively close
因为我们知道激光武器最怕的就是雾霾（大气层内远距离衰减）
because the atmosphere accuses the laser beam over longer distances making ineffective
你还得有高能激光，还得让它随时在天上待命
You also have to have these airborne lasers in the air all the time or cruising close
或者飞到发射井附近、或者国家边界附近，而这又会增加两国紧张形势
to the known launch positions or national borders something which was raised functions even more
如果在第一阶段你没法接近导弹
If you can't get the missile when it's in boost phase then
那第二阶段则是拦截的最好机会
the second mid-course phase when it's in space is the next best place to attack
这个阶段持续时间最长可达20分钟，但在此期间导弹可以采取反拦截措施
This is the longest phase lasts up to 20 minutes but it's here that the ICBM can fight back with countermeasures
许多洲际导弹可以带很多弹头
Many ICBMs can hold more than one warhead
国际条约里限制是十个，没错，十个弹头可以分散到不同地方进行打击，但还有别的
international treaties limited to 10, yes, 10 separately targeted warheads but that's not all
为了迷惑对方的侦测、追踪系统
To confuse the defenders detection and tracking systems
导弹还会带诱饵球，会在弹头释放时充气
a missile will also carry decoys, mylar balloons which will inflate when warheads attack
它们和导弹剩余部分、多个弹头飘在一起
These float along with the missile debris and the warheads and often are
形状颜色和弹头一样
shaped and painted to look like warheads
对于雷达防御系统来说，这些都是潜在目标，但你该拦截哪个呢？
To the defenders radar systems these all look like potential targets but which ones do you go for
反导导弹数量有限，选错了，真弹头就冲你来了
With a limited number of ABMS available pick the wrong ones and you will be letting the real warheads through
历史上有过几次太空中拦截导弹的系统性尝试
There have been several attempts to make systems that try to destroy the missiles when they're in space
最有名的就是里根的“星球大战”计划，也叫“战略防御倡议”
The most famous was Reagan's Star Wars or the Strategic Defense Initiative
计划原定在太空建一个防御系统，使用高能激光
This was to build a space-based defense system using high-powered lasers
在导弹再入地球时就把多个弹头摧毁
to disable multiple targets before they fell back to earth
然而当时的技术并没法做到这些
The technology on the other hand was not capable of delivering
别说八十年代了，就搁现在也还在图样
this during the 80s and be honest it only really started young practical now
而到目前为止唯一证明能有效拦截有限范围内有限目标的则是动能拦截器
The method which has been proven to work although on a limited scale and against
a limited number of targets just normally one at a time so far is the kinetic impact or kill vehicle
这种非爆炸装置重量在4公斤左右
These are small non explosive devices away around four kilos or ten pounds
用拦截导弹发射至太空来拦截来袭目标
that are launched into space on an ABM to intercept the incoming targets
它们释放到太空后
These are released once in space and have onboard
利用自带的制导、推进系统去和来袭的弹头与诱饵弹同归于尽
navigation thrusters so they can be guided to crash into the incoming warheads or decoys
进入21世纪后，这一思路拓展成了多重杀伤载具
In the mid 2000 this idea was expanded with the MKV or Multiple Kill Vehicle
防御方拦截弹携带十多个拦截器
The defenders carrier missiles with a number of these maybe a dozen or so
释放后形成集群，理论上能摧毁所有目标
and once released they would effectively form a cloud that in theory would target all the potential targets
无论是真实弹头还是诱饵弹
both real and decoy
但这仍然很难做到
But this is still an extremely difficult operation to pull off
因为导弹侦测系统需要配备高分辨率X波段雷达
As the missile detection systems have to use high-resolution x-band radar
还要有先进的图像识别技术来识别所有潜在目标
and advanced image recognition to be able to identify all the potential targets
从诱饵弹和导弹其他部分中区挑出真正的弹头
and weed out the warheads from the missile debris and the decoys
之后再把这些坐标发送给拦截器，拦截器自行制导、锁定并拦截
It then sends what it thinks are the real target coordinates to the MKV's own tracking system for the final lock
这个过程中、拦截器和目标都是以每小时三万公里的速度飞行
All whilst the MKV and the target have a
closing speed of more than 30,000 kilometers or 18,000 miles an hour
另一个问题是潜在目标的数量
The other problem here is the number of potential targets
绝大多数情况发射的不止一发洲际导弹
It's extremely unlikely that just one ICBM will be launched
真正的洲际导弹攻击是一口气从好几个地方射好几发的
In a real attack dozens of ICBMs will be launched and arrived in ways from different launch locations
每一发都带有多弹头和诱饵弹
each with multiple warheads and decoys
光这就够防御系统吃一壶了
This will just simply overwhelm any defense system
即使袭击规模有限，攻击方可能只有20%的命中率
Even if it was a limited attack, the attacker has probably could get only 20% of rewards through
但防御方追求的是100%
but the defender shoot out 100%
虽然这在现实中不太可能
something that in real life with current technology would be virtually impossible
如果第二阶段拦截失败，那就只剩第三阶段了，但这时间非常短
If this fails then there is just the final terminal phase but this is very short
通常小于一分钟，此时导弹速度也高达每秒八公里
typically under a minute and the velocity of the warheads is going on five miles or eight kilometers per second range
早期的该阶段防御系统使用核弹头来“以毒攻毒”
Early defense systems use nuclear-tipped missiles which would explode near the approaching warheads in an attempt
通过核爆时的电磁脉冲来摧毁攻击方弹头的制导系统
to knock out their guidance and arming eletronics with an electromagnetic pulse
但随着新的抗辐射技术的成形
But with newer radiation hardened control electronics
以及在本土国高空核爆带来的危害，这种策略已经放弃了
and the side effects of dozens of Hiroshima site high-altitude air burst above your own territory, the idea was dropped
这意味着目标城市的指挥中心、导弹井
This means that the area being targeted the city command center missile silo
甚至是舰队，都要配备拦截弹
or even a flotilla of ships must have ABMs and very close
而对于没有这些的地区，拦截弹也没时间飞到这些地方去拦截
For undefended areas there would be simply too little
time for an ABM to intercept a warhead before it detonated
要么使用动能拦截器飞过去同归于尽
Again these systems are either kinetic weapons which have to hit the target
要么用近炸引信在目标旁边引爆
or have proximity fuses and detonate close to the target
目前的系统虽然在测试中有效，但从未在实战中得到验证
Current systems can launch multiple targets and in tests have worked but none have been proven in a real-world attack
最后，我们还是没法防御全面打击
In the end we just still cannot defend against an all-out attack
那我们只能用六十年代的老办法，名叫MAD
So we have to fall back on the 60-year old policies of the appropriately named MAD
全称“相互保证毁灭战略”
MAD, Mutually Assured Destruction
双方都无法承受毁灭性打击，就都不会动手了
in order to keep the peace by making nuclear war just not worth the consequences for either side
就像丘吉尔说的——“能吵吵就尽量别动手”
As Churchill said meeting jaw to jaw is better than war
所以感谢大家观看，还是提醒一句
So as always thanks for watching but before I go I would just like to remind you of
这个YouTuber的频道Curious Droid
the Curious Droid merchandise store and also the curious droid Facebook groups
字幕翻译给虫，给虫自己也会做些科普
now open we've suggest ideas for new videos and finally you can now translate
可以提建议，提内容，虽然我会的也不多
any of the curious droid videos if you are a non English speaker with the
最后如果喜欢视频的话
community contributions which we also have a video on if you're unsure just
记得点赞投币收藏分享关注
checking the uploading videos so again thanks for watching and please subscribe, rate, and share